<div>
<p><b>About the Emory Women Writers Resource Project</b></p>
<p>The current Emory Women Writers Resource Project site represents the
joining of the original EWWRP site and the Womens Genre Fiction site.</p>

<p>The Emory Women Writers Resource Project began in 1994 as
pedagogical tool designed to offer graduate and undergraduate students
the opportunity to create critical editions of texts. Examples of
student editions are available under the Essays link. The project has
expanded each year to include new texts. The texts are digitized by
graduate students, and marked up in XML according to the Text Encoding
Initiative standards. The texts have been selected in consultation
with Dr. Sheila Cavanagh of the English Department, the editor of the
site.</p>

<p>In 2002 the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) awarded a
grant to create an online database of American and British genre
fiction written by and about women in the late nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries to the Emory Women Writers Resource Project
(EWWRP) of Emory University. Spanning from the 1860's through the
1920's, the period addressed by the project roughly coincides with the
peak of the popularity of dime novels. Emory's Robert W. Woodruff
Library houses an extensive collection of detective, crime, and
romance novels and provided the source texts for this digitization
project. The Women's Genre Fiction Project publishes an unprecedented
collection of female-authored and female-centered texts from a range
of genres, as well as the largest searchable database of digitized
genre fiction.</p>

<p>During the three-year project, staff selected, digitally converted,
proofread, and encoded 100,000 pages from hundreds of literary
texts. All texts were marked up in XML, using the Text Encoding
Initiative's (TEI) Document Type Definition (DTD). Project staff
captured pages as archival quality TIFF images and archived a copy of
each file for preservation purposes. All encoded files have been added
to the existing database that hosts the EWWRP.</p>

<p>The project's editorial board expects the project to accomplish two
principal objectives. First, the database will expand access to a
significant facet of American and British culture. The electronic
publication of women's genre fiction makes these novels widely
available in searchable, digital form for the first time. By
disseminating texts that have been under-represented in library
collections, the database will facilitate scholarly work and teaching
in a range of areas, including American and British history and
literature, late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century culture, and
women's studies. Second, publishing these works in electronic format
will reduce unnecessary handling of the fragile originals, thus
helping to preserve them.</p>

<p><b>
Navigating the Site</b></p>
<p>The site is divided into collections: <a href="genrefiction">Genre
Fiction</a>, including the 250 novels digitized by the Beck Center
under the NEH grant; <a href="earlymodern">Early Modern</a> literature
through the 18th century; <a href="twentiethcentury">Early 20th
century</a> literature; <a href="worldwarI">World War I poetry</a>; <a
href="nativeamerican">Native American</a> texts; <a
href="abolition">Abolition, Freedom, and Rights</a>; and <a
href="advocacy">Women's Advocacy</a> texts. Some texts appear in more
than one collection. </p>

<p>The texts may be accessed by searching or browsing. In the browse
view the default listing is by author, but using the links below the title of the work, users may view texts by title, ethnicity of the author,
geographic location of the author, subject, publisher, or
genre. In addition, where spine images are available, books may be
viewed as on a bookshelf. Clicking the spine will take the user to the
table of contents. </p>

<p>Users may search by keyword from any page; if you are in a
collection, the keyword query will search that collection. To search
the entire collection select the Emory Women Writers Resource
Project link at the top of the collections. In addition, users may
access an advanced search which allows searching by author, title,
date, and subject fields. The advanced search offers suggestions based
on the material in the collection.</p>

<p>Whether browsing or searching, the list view presents the first 20
results. To view more results click "Next" on the navigation bar, or
use the jump list on the right to jump to any set of 20. </p>

<p>Search results are returned with the highest frequency of hits
first. To see the search result in a brief context, click on the
number of hits. To view the text with highlighted results, click on
the table of contents in the keyword view. Clicking on the title in
the results list goes to the table of contents of the work.</p>

<p><a href="credits.php">Site Credits</a></p>
</div>

